What you doing?
You said clean up.
I'm cleaning up.
You can't just throw
everything in the closet.
Hey, you can tell me
what to do
or you can tell me how to do it,
but you can't do both;
this isn't sex.
What if someone looks in there?
They're just coming
over for dinner.
No one's gonna
look in the closet.
Well, you don't know that.
What if someone's
looking for the bathroom
and they open that door?
Could work out.
For all we know,
there's a toilet
in there somewhere.
Fine. But after tonight,
we need to get a handle
on this mess.
You know what we should do?
We should show the
closet to Sheldon.
Why?
Are you kidding?
He's like a savant
at organizing.
Everything in his apartment
has a label on it.
Including his label maker,
which has a label
that says "Label Maker."
And if you look really close
at that label maker label,
you'll see a label
that says "Label."
He's our guest;
we can't just ask him
to straighten our closet.
No, we wouldn't ask him.
We'd just show him the closet
and let the goblins in his head
take it from there.
Hey, guys, come on in.
Hi.
Ooh, it smells good.
Thanks.
And, Sheldon, I know tonight's
the night you eat Thai food,
so I went to the Asian market,
got all the ingredients
and made it from scratch.
Oh, you shouldn't have.
Oh, it's my pleasure.
No, you really shouldn't have.
I brought my own.
You stopped
and got him takeout?
I had no choice.
He kept kicking
the back of my seat.
Sheldon, I've been
cooking all day.
Well... now don't you
feel silly.
Show him the closet.
♪ Our whole universe
was in a hot, dense state ♪
♪ Then nearly 14 billion years
ago expansion started... Wait! ♪
♪ The Earth began to cool
♪ The autotrophs began to drool,
Neanderthals developed tools ♪
♪ We built the Wall
♪ We built the pyramids ♪
♪ Math, Science, History,
unraveling the mystery ♪
♪ That all started
with a big bang ♪
♪ Bang! ♪
♪ The Big Bang Theory 6x19 ♪
The Closet Reconfiguration
Original Air Date on March 13, 2013
== sync, corrected by elderman ==
These spring rolls are amazing.
Good job, Bernadette.
That's the takeout
that Sheldon brought.
Oh, well, I'm sure
they wouldn't have tasted
nearly as good if I hadn't tried
your food first.
Howard, did you want
your clothes arranged
seasonally or by color?
Color's fine.
Wrong, they'll be
arranged seasonally.
Sheldon, aren't you gonna spend
a little time with Amy?
Oh, it's okay, I'm used to it.
The other day at Whole Foods,
he spent an hour
optimizing the cheese aisle.
Yeah, and some thanks I got.
The assistant manager
chased me out
with an artisanal salami.
His quirks
just make you love him more.
Someone please agree with me.
Subtitles downloaded from www.OpenSubtitles.org
Sheldon, come on.
It's getting late.
Time to go.
Oh, five more minutes.
That's what you said
five minutes ago.
Amy and Penny
are already in the car.
Let's move it.
How come I never get to do
anything I want to do?
You know, if he really wants
to stay and finish,
I can give him
a ride home.
Please, Leonard!
He said it's okay!
Sheldon, it's--
Wait, I can go home
without you? Bye!
Howard, I have
a few questions.
I found three
bowling pins.
Now, do you juggle these,
or are you missing seven?
Juggle.
You health nuts kill me.
Oh, my God,
it's beautiful!
Look, he found the
juggling pins I hid.
Uh, just a couple
more items.
Howard, I found this letter
from your dad in a box.
Now, based on
the content,
it could either be filed...
Whoa, you opened this?
Well, I had to find out if
it was personal correspondence
or memorabilia.
Now, as I was saying,
based on the content...
I couldn't be less interested.
Now, come on,
I'll take you home.
Howard, don't you want to
know what's in the letter?
If I wanted to know,
I would've opened it years ago.
The closet looks great.
Let's get out of here.
Wait, can I
bring this box
of extra shirt buttons
to sort on the ride?
Do whatever you want.
Thanks.
Oh.
Great party.
You know, when I
first met Howard,
he would pull his scrotum
out of his shorts
and say, "Oh,
I sat in gum."
What is your point?
Well, it's just kind of weird
how grown up he is now.
Happily married guy
throwing dinner parties.
Really? You couldn't
just say that?
You had to tell
the scrotum story?
Trying to paint a picture.
Yeah, it was
a nice change of pace
not eating takeout
around a coffee table.
Mm, you know, we could
throw a dinner party, too.
Maybe even ask everyone
to get dressed up.
Sure.
Just, when you say
"dressed up,"
you mean
nice clothes, right?
Not, like, capes
and tights and crap?
Yeah.
Although...
No!
Howie, you okay?
Yeah, I just...
couldn't sleep.
Told you you shouldn't
have espresso after dinner.
I know the little cups
make you feel big,
but it's not worth it.
It's this stupid letter.
Did you read it?
No.
You must be curious.
Of course I'm curious.
I haven't seen
the man since,
oh, I was a little kid.
And a letter shows up
on my 18th birthday?
What's that about?
Why don't you read it?
Maybe he apologizes or
explains why he left.
He abandoned
me and my mother.
Why does he deserve
a chance to explain anything?
I get that.
So, what do you
want to do with it?
Something I should've done
a long time ago.
Really? Are you sure?
Yep.
Feel better?
I do.
Great.
Neither one of us is
tall enough to reach that.
I can't believe
he set it on fire.
Yeah, just seeing that letter
really freaked him out.
And he was already
having a tough day
'cause he accidentally wore
my pants to work.
I don't know why he was upset.
They were bigger on him than me.
Boy, I'm really curious
what's in that letter.
Me, too, but I guess
now we'll never know.
Well, you said Sheldon read it.
Why not ask him?
I can't do that.
What kind of wife would I be
if I didn't respect
my husband's privacy?
What if I ask Sheldon,
you just happen to be
in the room?
That works.
Okay.
Blech.
Like cleaning out the entire
building's belly button.
Hey, Sheldon.
Oh, hello.
What can I do for you ladies?
You have
something we want.
Oh, dear.
My mother warned me
this is what happens
to pretty boys in the big city.
No, we just
want information.
Oh.
Oh, I've got that in spades.
Ravage me.
We heard you read the letter
from Howard's father.
I did.
What did it say?
Yeah...
I can't tell you that.
I'm bound by closet organizer/
organizee confidentiality.
Sheldon, that's
not a real thing.
Well, neither is the rule
that you have to
hold your girlfriend's hand
at the movies.
You know.
That doesn't stop you
from pawing at me
like you're a bear and I'm
a trash can full of sweets.
Why do you even care?
Just tell us what it says.
Control over the information
contained in that letter
belongs to Howard.
By happenstance,
I came to know it.
That doesn't give me the right
to disseminate it freely.
Come on. Look, the letter was
found in Bernadette's closet.
Doesn't that count
for something?
Are you pointing out
that California
is a community property state,
and since Howard and Bernadette
are married,
the intellectual property
contained in that letter
is jointly owned
by the two spouses?
Yeah, obviously.
Well played.
Sometimes I don't give you
enough credit, Penny.
Dude, you made
the right choice
coming to me for help
with this party.
Actually, all I did
was invite you.
Well, put your mind at ease.
I'm here to make sure
your dinner party
kicks Howard's
dinner party's ass.
Now, the first thing
we need is a theme.
I'm thinking...
ah, turn-of-the-century
Moulin Rouge.
I'm thinking you need
a testosterone patch.
Penny and I
just want to do
something low-key.
You know, cocktails,
light jazz music,
hors d'oeuvres.
So your theme is
"I saw a rerun of Mad Men
and bought some crab puffs
from Trader Joe's"?
Hate to miss that.
Hey, where have you been?
Oh, Leonard.
If I was prone to sarcasm,
I'd say I was pulling off
a major heist
at the museum
of laundry baskets.
One, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
I meant, "Golly, Sheldon,
you've been gone a long time."
Oh. Yeah, well, I was waylaid
by Penny, Bernadette and Amy.
They made me reveal
confidential information
about Howard's father.
What information?
I can't tell you that.
I am bound by closet organizer/
organizee confidentiality.
Well, come on,
we won't tell anyone.
Sorry, badgering me won't work.
What you should have said is,
"It's pointless
to keep this a secret
because Penny will tell us."
Fine, then that.
All right, I'll tell you.
My goodness,
everyone's on their game today.
This is really fun.
Yeah, it's nice to get
dressed up once in a while.
Yeah, and hors d'oeuvres
are delightful.
As is the company.
Aw.
My shirt is itchy
and I wish I were dead.
Hey, uh, listen,
everybody.
Before Howard gets here,
let's all just agree
to not bring up the letter
from his father.
Of course.
Sure. Absolutely.
If I say yes,
can we turn off
that Latin orgy music?
Ridiculous that we
still have to walk
up all these
flights of stairs.
Yeah, try doing it
in heels.
I am.
Wait.
There's something
I have to tell you.
What?
I know what was
in your dad's letter.
Sheldon, I swear to God,
I'm gonna kill you!
Hey!
I made him tell us.
What? "Us"?
Who else knows?
I know.
Me, too.
Same here.
Shame on all of you.
You know, too.
Couldn't leave him
with one friend, could you?
So everybody knows
what's in that letter
except for me?
Yes, it's six
against one.
Stand down, sir.
How could you do this?
I'm sorry.
If you want, we
could tell you.
No, I don't
want to know!
I mean,
I do, but...
I got to go.
Used me as a human shield?
I panicked.
He looked taller than usual.
Howard?
In here.
I'm sorry.
I should have left it alone.
It's okay.
Sorry I ran off like that.
What are you looking at?
Uh, pictures of my dad and me
when I was a kid.
That's nice.
I got to tell you,
as angry as I am
at Sheldon for blabbing,
he did a hell of a job
organizing this closet.
Look at this.
"Photos of Wolowitz family
before father left forever."
Check out nine-year-old Howie
with cornrows.
Neither race was happy
to see me with those.
Think you could take a break?
Why?
Got a little surprise for you.
Come on.
Oh, honey...
I am in no mood
to have sex tonight.
I'll lay there
if you absolutely
have to have it, but... Oh.
What are you guys doing here?
When you left,
you weren't sure whether or not
you wanted to know
what was in your dad's letter,
so we came up with
kind of a cool solution.
Oh, yeah, what's that?
It's simple, really.
It occurred to me
that knowing and not knowing
can be achieved by creating
a macroscopic example
of quantum superposition.
The-the principle
that a physical system
exists partially in all
its possible states at once.
We were all thinking it, really.
It was kind of the elephant
in the room, so...
Anyway, um, I realize
if we each present you
with an account
of what your father wrote
to you,
only one of which is true,
and then we don't tell you
which one it is,
you will forever be
in a state
of epistemic ambivalence.
Yeah.
And I said
if it wasn't epistemic,
we might as well not do it.
Sit down, honey.
Raj, you're up.
Okay, um...
It was a card
for your 18th birthday.
Inside it said,
"Happy birthday, Howard.
I love you. Dad."
Oh, and it was
a Far Side card,
the one where the frog
has its tongue stuck
to the underside of an airplane.
Thinks it's a fly.
Silly frog.
So funny.
Sheldon.
It was a map leading
to the lost treasure
of famous pirate One-Eyed Willy.
Nice try.
That's the plot for Goonies.
Told you.
Don't.
Amy.
You didn't know it,
but your father was
in the auditorium
at your high school graduation.
And he cried
because he was so proud of you.
Really?
Or that's complete poppycock
which Amy made up.
It still could be the map.
Penny.
It was a letter explaining
that your dad wasn't
who he said he was.
Eventually, his other life
caught up to him,
and the only way to keep you
and your mom safe was to leave.
I would like
to change mine.
The pirate's name
was Peg-Leg Antoine.
Now it's completely different
from Goonies.
No, it's not.
Don't.
Okay, my turn.
Your dad wrote about how family
is the most important thing,
and that you should never
throw it away like he did.
Hmm.
Bernadette.
Inside the envelope
was a picture
of your dad holding you
the day you were born.
On the back he wrote,
"Howard, my son,
my greatest gift."
You okay?
Yeah.
I'm terrific.
So...?
Which one
do you think it is...
matey?
Actually, I don't want to know.
I...
want all of them to be true.
Well, one of them is.
That's pretty cool.
Thank you, guys.
Hey, it's still early.
Why don't we go back
and have that party?
Yeah, cool.
Okay? Good.
You know, surprisingly,
uh, the letter
from your father
wasn't the most
interesting thing
I read in the closet.
Bernadette's diary
has some saucy passages.
Sheldon, don't you dare!
Th-There's nothing
to worry about.
Your secret's safe with me.
That's more like it.
Although copyright law
would allow me to quote snippets
in the context of a review.
Glad you're
feeling better.
Me, too.
If I'd known
we were gonna be dancing,
would have worn my flats.
This turned out
pretty well, huh?
Yeah, I think so.
I agree.
That is, if you've never been to
or heard of a party before.
If you'd let me pierce your
brain with a hot needle
in the right place, you'd
be happy all the time.
Uh, Penny,
I-I have a couple of questions
about your closet.
Is there any reason
you're keeping
this dead goldfish?
Damn, I forgot to feed him.
And that I had him.
Well, now, did you also
have a dog?
Because I found what appears to
be a battery-operated chew toy.
Party's over!
== sync, corrected by elderman ==
Best watched using Open Subtitles MKV Player